<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2020-09-22T03:33:26+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Computational Literary Studies (CLS)</title><subtitle>The priority programme SPP 2207 Computational Literary Studies (CLS), funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG), is dedicated to developig and establishing innovative computational methods in the field of literary studies
</subtitle><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><entry><title type="html">Anomaly-based large-scale analysis of style and genre reflected in the use of stylistic devices in medieval literature</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Anomaly-based_large-scale_analysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anomaly-based large-scale analysis of style and genre reflected in the use of stylistic devices in medieval literature" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Anomaly-based_large-scale_analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Anomaly-based_large-scale_analysis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joachim Denzler &amp;amp; Sophie Marshall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is the development of a novel distant-reading tool for the
quantitative analysis of the use of rhetorical devices. The developed methods will be applied
for a comparative stylometric analysis of three medieval genres: the Middle High German
adaptations of the trois matières. From the viewpoint of medieval studies, we aim for
identifying genre-specific stylistic differences between romances of antiquity, Arthurian
romances, and chanson de geste adaptations of the 12 th and 13 th century. Up to now,
quantifiable similarities and differences of these genres regarding their use of rhetorical
devices have not been analysed. Such an analysis would be valuable for the controversial
discussion about the medieval concepts of ‘genre’ and the genre-awareness of medieval
authors as well as for assessing the relevance of rhetorical devices taught in medieval
schools for the practice of vernacular authors. To this end, we intend to analyse whether
selection, use, and frequency of rhetorical devices depend on the scene type and whether
characteristic differences can be attributed to genres or just different authors or dates of
origin. Such a broad analysis requires computational methods for distant reading, which do
not yet exist for the detection of stylistic devices to a satisfactory degree, not to mention for
Middle High German texts. For this purpose, we seek to develop novel methods for
detecting rhetorical devices based on methods from the fields of anomaly detection as well
as active and life-long machine learning. In this context, we consider rhetorical devices as
‘anomalies’, as deviations from the quantitative norm established by the greater part of the
corpus, which can be detected using statistical methods (e.g., a chiasmus is an anomaly
amidst non-chiastic constructions). To reduce time-consuming manual annotation tasks to a
minimum, we propose to employ active learning techniques in a semi-supervised scenario
with the human in the loop: Based on an initially unsupervised process of detecting stylistic
anomalies, the system refines itself in an interactive process by actively asking the user for
annotations for a few informative examples. Furthermore, we intend to integrate prior
theoretical knowledge provided by experts into the anomaly detection procedure for
filtering out obvious false positives and steering it towards certain rhetorical devices. In this
project, we will focus on two exemplary stylistic devices: the chiasmus as a figure of
repetition and the metaphor as a trope. The latter can be seen as an anomaly as well due to
the unusual interactions between words from different domains, reflected in their word
embeddings. Since such embeddings need to be learned from huge corpora, which are not
available for low-resource languages such as Middle High German, we also strive for
developing a technique to adapt such embeddings learned on New High German corpora to
Middle High German.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Joachim Denzler &amp; Sophie Marshall</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The beginnings of modern poetry - Modeling literary history with text similarities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Beginnings_of_Poetry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The beginnings of modern poetry - Modeling literary history with text similarities" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Beginnings_of_Poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Beginnings_of_Poetry.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simone Winko &amp;amp; Fotis Jannidis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition of realism, the dominant art form of the 19th Century, to early modernism at the turn to the 20th Century has been seen by contemporaries then and literary history since then as a profound change affecting many formal and content-related aspects. This is also true for poetry. But while today only a small group of poets and poems is seen as ‘modern’, the contemporaries applied this attribute to much more texts as can be seen, for example, by looking at all the anthologies with modern poetry published around 1900. One of the main goals is to understand this discrepancy: Does literary history ignore the modern trends in those other poems or did the contemporaries perceive change and innovation where there was none? In order to answer this question we will look at the similarity of texts, assuming that more modern texts will be more similar with each other than with more traditional texts. Similarity is always related to a specific perspective. The dimensions under which contemporaries then and literary historians today see the main differences between the poetry of realism and early modernism are mostly the same: new themes, new forms and a new way of addressing and expressing emotions in poems. We will cover all these aspects but with different degrees of effort to innovate the methods used. The development of new methods will concentrate on semantic text similarity and sentiment or more exact emotion analysis. Measuring the text similarity of short texts like poems is quite challenging, but since the introduction of word2vec and other forms of word embeddings the situation has improved dramatically. Applying these approaches to historical texts and especially to a genre like poetry is another challenge: The vocabulary of poetry is markedly different even compared to that of other literary genres. It is characterized by the usage of old-fashioned words and neologisms, many of which are compound words. Determining which approach to word embeddings is preferable for our use cases and how they can be used to represent short texts focusing on dimensions like general semantics is one focus. The other is the development of an historical sentiment lexicon including emotions without anachronism. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Simone Winko &amp; Fotis Jannidis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CHYLSA (Children’s and Youth Literature Sentiment Analysis)*</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-CHYLSA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CHYLSA (Children’s and Youth Literature Sentiment Analysis)*" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-CHYLSA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-CHYLSA.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berenike Herrmann, Arthur Jacobs, Gerhard Lauer &amp;amp; Jana Lüdtke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotional involvement is of pivotal importance when children learn to read, tell, and share stories. This crucial dimension of cultural literacy has received surprisingly little attention within literary studies, psychology, and digital humanities. Taking a large-scale and data-driven approach, the most promising method to assess emotional information in children’s reading material is sentiment analysis. It allows the analysis of larger text corpora to find verbal emotional patterns potentially guiding young readers’ affective-aesthetic responses to literary texts – to characters, events, narrator/voice, and poem lines. Consequently, it facilitates modeling the role of emotions in the interaction of emerging literary literacy and social-cognitive development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, standard sentiment analysis tools were developed in the (industry-driven) framework of opinion mining and need domain-adaptation to literary discourse. Also, disconnected from psychological THEORIES, they often encode models of affect, emotion, and mood that are psychologically questionable, and lack empirical cross-validation. In (digital) literary studies, only a very small number of studies applies sentiment analysis to children’s literature. Most importantly, standard sentiment analysis outside the scope of children’s literature does not assess aesthetic and indirectly communicated feelings. Consequently, its application to literary texts in general and particularly to children’s literature has conceptual and methodological limitations, specifically for historical, non-English, and highly AESTHETIC texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose to advance sentiment analysis of literary texts for young readers in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) by building a representative and balanced corpus of children’s literature from different literary epochs and across a variety of genres,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) by using this corpus for a domain adaptation of sentiment analysis for literary texts that is also pioneering within NLP for its psychologically approved modeling of AFFECTS and aesthetic feelings, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) by testing the validity of these tools via predicting and assessing children’s reading experience and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research is motivated by the theoretical frameworks of social-interactive theory of narrative learning, the Neurocognitive Poetics Model of literary reading (https://www.researchgate.net/project/Neurocognitive-Poetics), and a systematic and historical philological account of situated emotion-cognition in children’s literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Long title: Advanced sentiment analysis for understanding affective-aesthetic responses to literary texts: A computational and experimental psychology approach to children’s literature&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Berenike Herrmann, Arthur Jacobs, Gerhard Lauer &amp; Jana Lüdtke</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emotions in Drama</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Emotions_in_Drama.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emotions in Drama" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Emotions_in_Drama</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Emotions_in_Drama.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christian Wolff &amp;amp; Katrin Dennerlein&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the depiction and evocation of emotions are at the heart of dramatic production and poetological reflection since Aristotle quantitative drama analysis has neglected them so far. This is why the project aims at extracting emotions of characters and analyzing their appraisal with sentiment analysis. As emotions are highly depended on cultural and historical circumstances we chose to look at the historical phase starting from the  end of Thirty Years’ War up to restoration period in the 19th century during which German drama was established. This is a story of developing various subgenres which vary with respect to their thematization and presentation of emotions, mostly termed ‘Affekte’ in that period. The project relies on a corpus of German drama which is significantly enlarged compared to the available one for that period, the Textgrid corpus. It now comprises another 25 libretti of the Hamburger Gänsemarktoper from the period between 1678 and 1730, another 20 libretti from around 1800 as well as 20 texts from the strolling players. This enables us to research the most important dramatic (sub-)genre for the development of affect expression, the libretti of musical theatre, in its influences on spoken theatre.
In a first step models for the analysis of emotion in dramatic texts shall be evaluated with regard to their use for digital analysis. Retrievable linguistic as well as rhetorical means are specified and extracted for whole texts as well as for elements of dramatic texts specifically dedicated to the depiction of affects: stage directions, soliloquies, arias and endings of drama. Human annotators will specify for genre-specific subcorpora which emotions are mentioned (for example happiness, love, sorrow, envy). They will also annotate if these emotions are evaluated positively or negatively. In a next step algorithms of sentiment analysis shall be trained on this material. It is an important goal of the project to approve the method of sentiment analysis for its use on historical, especially fictional, corpora.
Having done all this work we should be able to identify pathos-strategies, id est passages of texts with a high arousal of emotions and to give first hints as to which emotions are thematized with which appraisal. Another objective is the revision of the history of the comic character and its relation to the emotion of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Christian Wolff &amp; Katrin Dennerlein</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Events in Narrative Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-EvENT.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Events in Narrative Theory" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-EvENT</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-EvENT.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evelyn Gius &amp;amp; Chris Biemann&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed project ‘Evaluating Events in Narrative Theory’ (EvENT) is an interdisciplinary approach to the formalization and analysis of events in narratives, based on a combination of Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods and concepts of Literary Studies. With a focus on the potential added value of using concepts of one discipline in the other one, the project includes the theoretical research of event concepts in both disciplines, the subsequent modeling and implementation for the automatic analysis of narrative texts, and the application of these systems for literary text analysis as well as in the context of information representation.
For the NLP research community, the theoretical discussions on narrative research questions and the operationalization of respective concepts in cooperation with Literary Studies will lead to advances on modeling events, sequences of events and a notion of event centrality/event ranking within long documents, with the additional challenge from the application domain, i.e. German literary texts.
For Narratology the modeling of events in cooperation with NLP will establish a testbed, which has not been available so far. Inductive development and application of categories for text analysis as performed in Literary Studies is complemented by a deductive approach, evaluating these categories on a variety of texts. This will lead to a twofold advancement of Narratology: with regard to theory the iterative modeling will generate theoretical findings about the formal narrative concept of events, with regard to the application of event concepts tools will be developed that can be applied for the computer-aided analysis of literary texts.
The automation of the analysis of events and event patterns in literary texts will address three areas, which align with the central role of events in narratology: (1) the formal description of events as well as narratological models of narrative constitution based on them, (2) the analysis of event- fulness, which will be based on the event II concept and the results of the first item, and (3) the operationalization of both for the automatic analysis and classification of narratives as well as the analysis of further narratological phenomena with respect to the specificity of related event types or patterns.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Evelyn Gius &amp; Chris Biemann</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">QuaDramA: Tracking Character Knowledge (Q:TRACK)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-QTrack.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="QuaDramA: Tracking Character Knowledge (Q:TRACK)" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-QTrack</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-QTrack.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nils Reiter &amp;amp; Marcus Willand&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q:TRACK’s research programme interlinks objectives in two research areas: literary and drama history and computational literary studies. In the first area, we are aiming at new insights about the way social knowledge is used to drive or solve the dramatic conflict in plays. We initially focus on the distribution and dissemination of knowledge within the single dramatic world of a play. An outcome of our work programme will be a formal model of the knowledge that each character as well as the audience has and gains within each segment (act, scene, appearance). Such a model, once it has been established, allows to visualize relations as well as drawing inferences. This can support close reading, but also facilitates comparing plays in a systematic way. Once such models can be created automatically, we will “zoom out” and look at dissemination patterns from a drama historical point of view, asking how they change over the centuries. A dissemination pattern is a generalization of the model found within a set of plays that is achieved by disregarding character names and allowing for some variation in the details. One such pattern might be that the relation triggering the anagnorisis is transmitted via a character not involved in the actual relation (as heralds, servants etc.).
In order to pursue our literary and drama historic goals, we thus systematically reconstruct constellations, modes and techniques of dramatic knowledge distribution. As an outcome of this project, we will gain insights into the blueprints of the art of playwriting. By taking a multi-perspectival viewpoint on character and audience knowledge we not only assure ourselves of a non-interpretive access to the plays. We also provide an intersubjective, meta-historical approach to the identification of text elements that supposedly function as sympathy and empathy control of readers and trigger dramatic effects as the purgation of emotions (catharsis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quadrama.github.io&quot;&gt;quadrama.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><summary type="html">Nils Reiter &amp; Marcus Willand</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relating the Unread - Network Models in Literary History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Relating_the_Unread.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relating the Unread - Network Models in Literary History" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Relating_the_Unread</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Relating_the_Unread.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ulrik Brandes &amp;amp; Thomas Weitin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a mixed methods approach to literary history, we intend to use network models of text relations to study how groupings emerge relative to the way text corpora have been compiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computational analysis of big data is as much about analysis as it is about the data itself. Corpora are almost never representative samples but opportunistic if not deliberate collections. Their composition is thus subject to systematic biases and affects the analysis of relations among texts, positions and status of texts relative to others, and the categorization of texts into groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will develop network models that integrate stylometric, semantic, and annotation data specifically for German-speaking and European Anglophone literatures of the 18th and 19th century, concentrating on novels and narratives. Our goal is to shine a different light on the establishment of genre conventions, subgenres and epoch style within this decisive period. From a socio-historical view point we focus on those texts and authors who were marginalized in the course of literary history, paying special attention to female writers and their positions alongside canonized texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to developing models and algorithms, we will use corpus manipulation as a heuristic method to study grouping processes and combined synchronic and diachronic corpus comparison. By detecting groups on a certain data level and watch them disappear on another, we will be able to foster our understanding of both historical and systematic text relations, and also of text groups within different periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><summary type="html">Ulrik Brandes &amp; Thomas Weitin</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structuring Literature - Variants and Functions of Reflective Passages in Narrative Fiction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Structuring_Literature.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structuring Literature - Variants and Functions of Reflective Passages in Narrative Fiction" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Structuring_Literature</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-Structuring_Literature.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anke Holler, Caroline Sporleder &amp;amp; Benjamin Gittel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All happy families are alike, each unhappy family is unhappy in its own way,” is the first sentence of Tolstoy’s “Anna Karenina” and one of the most talked about examples of reflection in fictional literature. Although even lay people distinguish such reflective passages in novels from passages that report actions or describe characters, reflective passages have not yet been established as a research topic in their own right in literary studies. Against this backdrop the project will combine insights from literary studies, linguistics, computational modelling and quantitative as well as qualitative text analysis to (i) elaborate and formalise a comprehensive concept of reflective passage, (ii) identify and classify such reflective passages in narrative fiction and (iii) explain their patterns of occurrence in roughly 350 years of literary history. To this end, the project will build on previous work for identifying reflection automatically in other text types as well as work on detecting related phenomena such as genericity and epistemic status and extend and combine these in a linguistically informed machine learning framework for finding author/narrator-attributed and character-attributed reflective passages in narrative fiction. By applying our models to a large corpus of German literature spanning several centuries, we will be able to identify periods in which reflection was particularly prevalent (“boom periods”). We will also look more closely at two prominent variants of reflective storytelling in literary history: essayistic and encyclopedic narration. We will compare automatically identified essayistic and encyclopedic passages in narrative fiction to non-fictional essays and encyclopedic texts and investigate similarities and differences with respect to style, topic and the epistemic status of clauses in order to identify internal as well as external functions of these passages in relation to the literary works and their socio-cultural context.  
Our contribution to the overall Priority Program “Computational Literary Studies” consists in (i) operationalizing a basic concept from literary theory by performing a qualitative and quantitative corpus study, (ii) enriching the methodic options to structure literary texts,  (iii) developing novel computational models for detecting reflection and related phenomena and demonstrating the usefulness of these algorithmic methods for literary historiography as well as the integration of their results into the qualitative research process, and (iv) creating and releasing a corpus manually annotated for reflection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><summary type="html">Anke Holler, Caroline Sporleder &amp; Benjamin Gittel</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Was ist wichtig? Schlüsselstellen in der Literatur</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-What_matters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Was ist wichtig? Schlüsselstellen in der Literatur" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-What_matters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/24/TP-What_matters.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Jäschke &amp;amp; Steffen Martus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dieses explorativ konzipierte Projekt beschäftigt sich mit der
Identifizierung und Charakterisierung von Schlüsselstellen in
literarischen Werken. Wir verstehen darunter Passagen, die für die
Textinterpretation von Expertenleser*innen besonders wichtig sind. In
einem Mixed-Methods-Ansatz wollen wir vorrangig empirisch untersuchen,
welche textuellen Merkmale literarischer Genres sich durch Zitat- und
Zitiermuster ergeben. Zweitens wollen wir untersuchen, ob sich
„Interpretationsgemeinschaften“ (S. Fish) profilieren lassen. Die
wesentliche Herausforderung des Projekts besteht darin, dass
Schlüsselstellen vermutlich durch komplexe, miteinander verwobene
intrinsische und extrinsische Faktoren gekennzeichnet sind, dass sich
Ansätze zur Identifizierung und Analyse solcher Faktoren noch in einem
frühen Stadium befinden und dass sich literatur- und
computerwissenschaftliche Forschung hierbei bislang nicht berühren. Wir
suspendieren vorerst die umstrittene Entscheidung über den Zusammenhang
zwischen extrinsischen und intrinsischen Faktoren. Stattdessen werden
wir die Praxis des Interpretierens beobachten, um zu erforschen, worin
der „poetische und rhetorische“ Charakter (G. Braungart) der tatsächlich
interpretatorisch bevorzugten Passagen besteht, was wir durch die
Struktur von Schlüsselstellen über den Text als Ganzes erfahren und
inwiefern sich diese Ergebnisse für die Verbesserung von Verfahren zur
automatisierten Analyse literarischer Texte nutzen lassen.Grundlage der
Untersuchung sind drei Typen von Korpora: literarische Werke,
bibliographische Metadaten und Aufsätze aus dem Bereich der Neueren
deutschen Literaturwissenschaft. Aus pragmatischen Gründen konzentrieren
wir uns auf die Genres „Erzählung“, „Novelle“ und „Drama“ aus dem
Bereich der neueren deutschen Literatur, weil wir auf bestehende Korpora
zurückgreifen können und Methoden der computergestützten
Literaturwissenschaft für diese Textarten tragfähige Ergebnisse erbracht
haben. Aus einer systematischen Perspektive konzentrieren wir uns bei
der Charakterisierung von Schlüsselpassagen auf stilistische
Eigenschaften, Figurengestaltung, Handlungsaufbau und Themen.
Gattungsgeschichtliche Aspekte werden eine wichtige Rolle spielen, da
wir kanonische Annahmen über die Struktur von narrativen und
dramatischen Texten berücksichtigen.Das Projekt ist in drei
Arbeitspakete gegliedert, die auf drei literarische Korpora abgestimmt
sind. Jedes Arbeitspaket enthält Aufgaben für Informatiker*innen und
Literaturwissenschaftler*innen. Die technischen Aufgaben konzentrieren
sich vor allem auf die Entwicklung von Methoden zur Extraktion,
Anreicherung und Analyse von Daten. Von literaturwissenschaftlicher
Seite werden insbesondere etablierte Theorien auf der Grundlage der
gewonnenen Daten überprüft und in praxeologischer Perspektive
ausgewertet. Die Projektergebnisse werden zu einem Konzept von
Schlüsselpassagen in Theorie und Praxis zusammengefasst.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><summary type="html">Robert Jäschke &amp; Steffen Martus</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zeta and Company - Measures of Distinctiveness for Computational Literary Studies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Zeta_and_Company.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zeta and Company - Measures of Distinctiveness for Computational Literary Studies" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Zeta_and_Company</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/project/2020/01/24/TP-Zeta_and_Company.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christof Schöch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methodological and epistemological paradigm of comparison is deeply rooted in the Humanities. Whether in qualitative or quantitative research, comparison allows to determine similarities and differences as well as affinities and contrasts; it thereby sharpens the analyst’s eye and adds specificity and meaningfulness to analyses. Against this backdrop, the purpose of Zeta and Company is to enhance our understanding of and propose improvements to quantitative, comparative methods of analysis of two or more collections of texts in the domain of Computational Literary Studies.
The focus will be on a key method in such comparative analyses, that of using statistical measures of distinctiveness that allow researchers to extract features (e.g. words or parts-of-speech) that are characteristic of a given group of texts when compared to another group of texts. In areas as diverse as Information Retrieval, Computational Linguistics and Computational Literary Studies, a wide range of statistical measures of distinctiveness have been developed for the fundamental task of identifying distinctive features. Three broad types of measures can be distinguished, each using quite distinct information for their calculations. The first type of measures takes as input the observed relative frequencies of the features in each of the two groups of texts taken together and compares them (e.g. log-likelihood test). The second type takes as input frequency distributions of the features built from each individual text in the two groups of texts (e.g. t-test). The third type takes as input the dispersion of the features across the texts in each group, that is, compares how equally distributed the features are across each group of texts (e.g. Zeta).
In order to reach a deeper understanding of measures of distinctiveness and propose improvements to their implementation and use, we will create and publish suitable benchmark corpora; we will analyse a significant range of existing measures of distinctiveness to determine and compare their statistical properties and formalize them in a joint conceptual model; based on this model, we will implement them in a common framework; we will implement and use several evaluation strategies to assess and compare these measures’ performance; and we will conduct an in-depth application study comparing several subgenres of the contemporary French novel (highbrow literary novelsand popular, lowbrow novels like crime fiction, romance and science fiction novels); finally, we will disseminate the key results of the study in academic publications as well as in the form of an interactive, pedagogical web portal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Steffen Pielström</name></author><category term="project" /><summary type="html">Christof Schöch</summary></entry></feed>